hi this is part four of the video series
what is the magellan course in part
three we looked at dialectical reasoning
in relationship to the evolution of the
structures of consciousness today in
part four we're going to look at
dialectics and dialectical reasoning
with respect to some contemporary
theories of cognitive development now
the interesting thing in doing this
video is that to look at the role of
dialectical reasoning in cognition we
are forced to choose what model of
development we will consider because the
model that we choose greatly influences
or determines how we answer this
question what is the role of dialectical
reasoning in cognitive development and
so in order to make these this choice in
this video transparent I wanted to go
over an overview of the different models
of development current models of
development little brief history of the
models of development now interestingly
enough when we look at the categories or
we categorize the models of development
we find that they themselves are set up
in a sort of polar relationship so for
the purposes of this video we are
considering Western in other words not
eastern versions and even within the
choice of the Western model of
development we are going to consider
primary
anglo-american and not the Contra
distinction which is more continental or
Marxian influence so I think this is you
know this itself links to the
dialectical mind of the dualistic mind
we have within just this inquiry the
problem of choosing East versus Western
versions of cognitive psychology and
then even within the Western version we
have the choice of biasing either an
anglo-american approach or a continental
Marxian approach and just to give you a
short taste of what that is
anglo-american approach is biased toward
nature in genetics and structuralism in
the continental Marxian approach is more
emphasizes culture nurture and related
nurture and relatedness relational ism
and also in terms of the anglo-american
the emphasis is on individual capacity
and the emphasis over here is on the
role of world or life experience and
you'll see that there are some of this
tension even within the anglo-american
field but within the American
anglo-american field we're going to look
at again another
in the preferences for modeling
cognitive development and this is a more
current very update division that that
that we will see and look at so within
this bias of primarily and
anglo-american models of cognitive
development we have to make sure that
we're limiting ourselves to that there
are two major camps that we can spell
out that we'll look at in a little more
detail today and the first camp
emphasizes skills in the second camp
emphasizes what we might say meaning
making we might say that for those of
you who know some of the significant
players here that the skills camp is
exemplified by Piaget and the Neal
Piaget and the meaning camp by Jane
Levenger and of course there's you know
a tendency to see this is a masculine
feminine tendency here - okay the skills
camp under tend to measure so what do
they measure they tend to measure
cognitive capacity and in the meaning
models tend to measure languages the
experiments in the skills models are
problem solving solving
whereas the experiments in the meaning
models are sentence completion tests in
how individuals process and manipulate
symbolic representation through length
primarily through language primarily
through language the skills models tend
to be more mathematically measurable and
reducible whereas the meaning models
tend to require a great deal of
interpretation not surprisingly and this
is a contention between them because
there's a there is a contention that
this is empirical work and this is less
than empirical this skills models tend
to emphasize what Piaget is known as
genetic epistemology in other words that
there are genetically inherited
structures that proceed in genetically
inherited stages and the meaning models
tend to look at dialectical movement in
life it's a little more fuzzy complex
the meaning-making people are attempting
to become established as being more
empirical and to make stronger
statements about structure of stages but
from the perspective of the skills
models the judgment is that they fail at
doing that because they're not as
mathematically measurable and then there
is a kind of line drawn in the sand
because from the perspective of the
meaning making peep models and within
the skills models themselves the only
genetic stages there are that all the
genetic stages go from pre-operational
these are Piaget Piaget's stages
pre-operational the concrete operational
to formal operational and at formal
operational we are measuring skills that
have to do with abstractions and so
according to the skills models there's
nothing higher than formal operations
although the current the most recent
models have outlined very very
high-level ways of working with
abstractions and abstract systems but in
this line of cognitive development
Theory there is no clear agreement that
there's any actual genetic stage above
formal operations whereas this line of
cognitive developmental models makes a
claim that there are actually stages and
adult development when you look at it
the whole picture
that are clearly beyond and discreet and
different and and novel from formal
operations stages and one of the
significance is is that it rejects a lot
of the claims of formal operations so it
rejects the claims of under that that
formal operations it makes meaning
beyond the operations or the claims of
formal operations and so that's one of
the reasons why we are going to look a
bit into this camp but we will emphasize
the more recent work in the
meaning-making area of cognitive
development because we are interested in
studying development cognitive
development beyond the level of formal
operations and only people studying in
this meaning making models have made a
claim that there are levels beyond
formal operations